We have a whole new technology that's the most important technology ever and you need a whole new infrastructure. Normally when we talk about the infrastructure, we're talking about the servers and the storage and the network. Here it goes all the way down to the mines of copper mines. Lots of hollow whites, but this thing is going to be it. It used to be when you built something, it was an engineering problem.
And here it feels like it really is a resource limitation. So whether it's tokens or not, we're pouring a ton of money into systems and then those systems are producing a result. And right now we're bottlenecked on the systems ability to actually match the resource we're pouring into them. The leading memory runner said the demand they have today will take them three years of capacity to supply. If this fund does what we think it will do, how do we see the world in five to ten years? America wins in the infrastructure dig. Damn, that would be awesome.
Today, A16Z is announcing the Machine Age Fund, a new fund dedicated to the infrastructure powering the next era of AI. I'm joined by Ben Horowitz, Ragle Ragle Ram, and Martin Casado to explain why we're launching it now and why we believe the next major bottleneck in AI isn't necessarily the model. It's everything underneath it. Chips, memory, networking, power, cooling, and data centers
are all being pushed beyond what they were originally designed to handle. At the same time, AI is changing an old rule of technology. Throwing money at an engineering problem didn't necessarily make it move faster. Increasingly, capital can be converted directly into compute and compute into more capable intelligence. We unpack what that shift means, where new infrastructure companies can break through and why a new generation of founders is returning to some of the hardest problems in computing.
Ben, Martin, Ragu. Thank you. All right. Thank you. I want to start with a mark quote to introduce this new fund. This is the biggest technological revolution of my lifetime. This is clearly bigger than the internet. The comps on this are the microprocessor, the steam engine, and electricity, or maybe the wheel. Guys, the Machine Age fund, please introduce it. Ben, start us off. Well, basically what's happened is we have a whole new technology that's the most important technology ever.
What happens every time there's a dramatic new way of using all of the things that we love infrastructure, you need a whole new infrastructure and never has it been more high impact as it is on this one. So not only do we need new chips, new system software, we need new ways of doing power.
we need to replace copper. I think like it's absolutely everything. So it's a very exciting time. So particularly for the kind of hardware aspects of this new era, we needed a new approach. Yeah, I would agree. Normally when we, at least in the computing, when we talk about the infrastructure world, we're talking about the servers and the storage of the network.
Here it goes all the way down to the copper mine. Lots of white spread, this thing is going to be. Now that's number one. On number two, I think what we have seen over the last three years is the steady increase of the capabilities of the models, where the model is no longer the model. And in fact, using AI, these models are getting better faster and faster and faster. Now the bottleneck is all what I call south of the model. And so that's why we need to work on that.
The only thing I'd add very quickly is we tend to follow founders and we've been watching over the last couple of years as the number of very strong teams going after complex hardware problems has increased. I don't know the actual numbers but I was trying to estimate it over the weekend. So I think we'd get maybe 5% of the deals from top founders would come in would be hard work before now. It's the north of 20% or 30% right now. So it was like the founder community which tends to be much smarter than the VC community has identified this as a very active area for innovation and they're responding.
I think 5% is probably generous. Yeah, it was very low. It was very low. Yeah, 3%. Yeah. And explain some of the macro conditions that have led to this change in terms of the surplus of harvest pursuing these ideas. Like what are they seeing that's enabling? Well, I mean the obvious is the demand for AI is basically infinite. And as a result of that, every part of the supply chain is under duress. I mean everything, including like materials used to make things like memory. It's also very interesting whether there's something unique about AI
Which, because the demand is infinite and growth is infinite, what you tend to worry about is the margin of companies, which is how efficient it is. Like normally you worry about growth. Can I just get people to buy this stuff? You don't have to worry about that here, the question, can you do this in a way that's profitable? And a lot of the efficiencies are actually strictly a physical limitation of hardware. And so even the business model of the AI wave is really putting a lot of stress on the existing systems because they weren't built for AI. They weren't built for those workloads. And I think there's just this...
This global observation that we actually need to change the core components to get that efficiency to help drive the growth and to drive the value of the businesses Yeah, and how did we know that demand is actually outpacing supply here rather than this being another hype cycle? Yeah, there are any number of cities. Firstly, it is that some of the smallest Judges of demand are calling huge purchasers
I mean, if you look at the hyperscale, right? Yeah. Their CAP expand has been exploding next year. Supposedly it's going to reach a trillion dollars collectively across the bay. Hyperscale is this year, it's about $700 billion, right? And if you think about it, there's a hyperscale as positioned in the industry. They see demand from everywhere, right? They see obviously the frontier labs, warning their compute. They see the AI native companies. They see the enterprise.
They see the US geography, the international geography. So if anybody has visibility, it is done. And they've been jacking up their capex, like it's never been seen before, right? So that's a clear, clear sign. And secondly, if you look at the companies that we see on a day-to-day basis, they are all different. All the application companies, the growth is insane. The frontier large, the growth is insane. It's been talking to them. So...
I would say on the demand side, the signals have never been clear that this is not a hype. And prices are going up. Like we've never seen prices go up on chips. The GDP prices went down. They always go down. If you look at the price curve, it's like this and then we've stuck with this. And we know only like 5, 10% of the others are working to stop today. I mean, if you look at the supply across the board, it's basically all booked out to 2028.
I mean, it's so bad, we've actually seen multi-day auctions for a few thousand GPUs. The other side of that, of course, is demand and as Raghu said, we've seen the fastest growing companies you've seen in the history of the industry. But also the unit of work that AI can do, the value of that unit of work keeps increasing, but underneath the coverage, the number of tokens that are consumed is going by orders of magnitude, right? If it's 100 tokens for chat or the agent, it's...
thousands of tokens, right? So you got expansion on both sides of demand. One is the unit of work is becoming more and more consumptive of tokens. And then secondly, one of the people that are forward that are going to be benefited. It's not just the developers. It's going to be all knowledge workers and then all of beyond that. So that's what we see. You said the key components in supply are sold out to 2027, maybe in 2028. 2028, yeah. What does it mean for an entire industry to be sold out that far?
I don't know if this has ever happened before. Do you guys recall? I mean, remember in the internet days when we were doing massive buildout, the majority that was actually being put in the ground was speculative and was dark? Remember the dark fiber in here, basically every GPU that's been created is already pre-sold. Yeah, we were quite there. I mean, there was a lack of bandwidth like in the 98-99 timeframe, but...
There wasn't that much real demand for it because there just weren't that many people on the internet. So it was a two-sided thing and the companies were all rushing there and needed more bandwidth theoretically, but there weren't the users on the other side to consume it necessarily and then to really consume a lot of bandwidth you have to do high bandwidth things like video, which weren't really viable for a number of reasons that had nothing to do with how much bandwidth was in the data center. So
It smelled similar, but it wasn't this. This is like we're flat out and people are reselling GPUs for four times what they bought them for and this kind of thing. Like it's just not, and then we're also out of power and cooling. And then on top of that, it's really hard to build because there's these incredible political headwinds going into it. So it's really unprecedented in my career.
that we've had anything like this. I want to give you a quick anecdote. So I was talking to a CFO of a large company, a large public company, who had historically been very resistant about going into the cloud. So they had a lot of servers and they were doing an inventory check and they realized that the memory in their servers had increased so much it could fund the entire migration to the cloud. So I just feel like we're in a very unusual situation. That's right. We're out of many things. Power, cooling, memory.
GPUs, like you name it, we're out of it. So the flagship conference for the industry is the one called Hotchips. It's going out in Stanford. And the leading memory ranger said the demand they have today will take them three years of capacity to supply it. It's just today. It's not even future demand. So in terms of being about everything simultaneously,
Is it because people just underestimated how good models would be, how useful they would be, they just couldn't have resumed the demand? Well, I don't even think it's that. I mean, this stuff came out of nowhere, right? We're only four years into this. So even if we had a perfect oracle once it started working, I don't think it would have been fast enough. We couldn't have built enough capacity. There's no way. And we're talking about...
like chip cycles, which tend to be three to four years. We're talking about breaking ground and building data centers, which is four to five years. And connecting, breaking down and building them and having power source. So like you either have to build your own power or like usually both you've got to build your own power and have power source, which is not easy. Yeah, we have an industry that's used, it's growing at 20, 30 percent. It's a great growth rate, right? And it's being connected to
And the software industry, it's typical to just as a base. So you can see the disconnect, right? So it's just wide-mang. And so why didn't this fund exist five years ago or seven years ago? Or why was it not a great category to invest in the same way, Brad? Well, I would say we're probably... I'd like to think for just in time, but we probably would have been well-suited to have it at least a couple of years ago.
Yeah, well, so you can actually point on basically every epoch to an independent company that came up. I clearly moved from the client from a mainframe to the client server. We saw a bunch of companies come up. They moved to the internet. This is what we got Cisco and Juniper, even in the mega data centers, which by the way was largely driven by the incumbent cloud providers verticalizing. You saw the arising of Arista. So there has been the ability to invest in
you know, silicon and hardware, but it's been relatively minor because the change has been relatively minor like one chip company, one switch company, where here everything is. And so I agree with Ben, we probably, you know, we probably could have started a little bit earlier, but the amount of change is so high now that it's just an obvious thing to do. And the other thing is the demand for intelligence is so vertical with really no end in sight. I mean,
Because every company that's adopted it is growing very fast in its usage. And then most companies haven't adopted it to a high degree. And then consumers are just getting started. And so it's going to probably, the demand for tokens is probably going to grow close to 1,000% a year, which you cannot grow supply that fat. Like we're not...
Like the amount of just work we're going to have to do across the board to get to the point where we can grow like infrared at that kind of rate is pretty vast. So I think there's a lot of investing opportunity on the way. And by the way, the other thing is like all the architectures of the hardware systems were built for a whole different era of computing. And so more than
Just we need more capacity. We need capacity to build there. There's lots of opportunities to build different kinds of infrastructure. Yeah, they're out reaching their The physics limits for what they were designed right? Like what Ben was talking about proper and so on and so forth and you could go across every one of these categories And you could find okay. This is the limit of this type of technology. So now he had a
Get some technical breakthroughs to get to the next one. Yeah, I want to dive deeper on that a man's type of thing as we've moved from chatbots to reasoning to agents to to multi agents each step has multiplied the number of tokens a single task takes up by orders of increasing order orders. Yeah, nobody likes to use AI more than a What does that keep happening instead of a leveling off and do you just see that happening? You know indefinitely just continuing to
Well, so there's a couple of answers to that. The first one is, for sure right now, if you look at like the way we're achieving scaling, the way we're doing it is through a lot of inference. So through a lot of token, right? If you think about what RL is, you know, so it's a lot of inference. If you think about chain of thought, it's a lot of inference. They think about long-running agents, of course, it's a lot of inference. And so that's just basically been one of the approaches that we've been using to scaling.
I think if you want to step back and say kind of what is the macro trend here? It used to be when you built something it was an engineering problem. You throw a bunch of engineers at it and that doesn't scale and that would have a natural law of engineering physics, which is what the Mythical Man month came from. And here it feels like it really is a resource limitation. So whether it's tokens or not, we're pouring a ton of money into systems and then those systems are producing a result. And right now we're bottlenecked on those systems ability to actually
match the resources we're pouring into them. And so I think like tokens right now is probably where we're on the scaling curve, but we don't have a natural regulator like engineering like we did before. So I think we should expect this to continue and we have to build a supply to support it. Yeah, like the similar thing about it is any problem that you have can be solved with enough infrastructure and money. And so until we run out of problems,
We're not going to run out of demand and that's the that's the challenge AI is answer to getting better and better is to use more yeah, right in friends is one basic building block that it keeps using over and over again And so that's why these tokens multiply. Yeah, even the auto catalytic effect So even the idea of using AI to create more AI like creating GPU kernel, of course is just using more AI
as part of the process. So again, one way that we think about it is in the past, money would come in, you have an engineering problem, we know that it takes two years, normally fails, it's a national governor and then you get the product on the other end. There's nothing between the money going in and then the hardware, creating intelligence. And so now we're just limited by our ability to create supply. So it's very, very different.
GPUs and all the solid is gone. Yeah, that's right. As long as you have the money, the GPUs and the data, you know, for the foreseeable future, you'll be able to scale these things. And it's fascinating because, you know, over the last decade it feels like there are so many, you know, people in the pervasive sentiment was there's too much money going to startups. We're overfinding these startups. There's too much money in venture capital. Say more about what that means because there used to be this...
sort of skepticism that the more money you put into the industry that, you know, there would be bigger outcomes. And now, you know, we're saying at the offsite that there's, to some degree, the market is as big as we collectively contribute to it. Yeah. So this is, look, the one thing we all knew in startup world is that if I have a two-year lead on you and you try and cast me by hiring a thousand engineers, you're going to wreck your company. Like, that never works.
It's a mythical man month. Nine women can't have a baby in a month. Like that's it. Like that never works. Okay, now that works. But it's not hiring 100,000 engineers. It's taking $3 billion and like lighting up a magnificent cluster. And then all the sun, you know, whatever grok can come out of nowhere and like, oh, all the sun is real or a Kimmy or what have you.
It's just like these leads, you can throw money at the problem and you can throw money at almost any problem and that works. And so that is just completely different than anything we've ever lived through. So we're, by the way, we're all psychologically adjusting to this. The chat gpt app has a billion weekly actives. There's about 30 million developers who are using, you know, relatively a big portion of compute demands.
How do we think about compute demands needs now and in the future in light of what people are actually doing with that? That's the progression, right? So, charging premiums is a casual option. It's coding for professionals, right? Now, using coding, you're not built amazing tools for knowledge workers. So, that's the next frontier. And now there are over a billion knowledge workers in the line, right? And for that, it's a lot of ways to go for that demand.
And by the way, the work that they do, all this work, growing automation and so on. And then they get to the back office, which is all the agents. So progressively each of these things unlocks, it's an order of magnitude more than that. I mean, just at the start of this. Well, and now you have Grockbot, which is kind of, you know, what happened with coding is kind of happening with all use of computer via Grockbot.
So we're in a whole nother wave of demand and most certainly there's gonna be more to come So it does seem quite Unlimited at the moment and we haven't even gotten into embodied AI or robots Which are gonna be another source of demand mark mark is expert but uh my understanding is a clock bug uses computer use which is just like
You know being sitting inside the computer title where I literally used it over the weekend to update my credit card with a bunch of services that I've been like lazy to do and cancel a bunch of subscriptions I mean this is not coding or whatever this is true computer years all of a sudden you can like possible in knowledge work case except they're all sitting inside of the computer I do I do think that that mark Andreessen is right is like the right analog here is like the steam engine or electricity in the following way like we've
We've introduced this new thing that you can turn to work. And there's some very obvious applications now. But there's probably 30, 40 years of throwing computer problems. I didn't think with the clear reward signal. And we're just starting. Like we've got language and code. That's it. And just starting computer use. But like what else are we looking at? We're looking at in terms of science, materials, biology. And then of course, creativity is a massive use. And so listen, we're not the very, very early part of a very long journey. And we've
Remove this key bottleneck, which is you know traditional software entering now of course you know bottlenecks will move and they'll be kind of more complexity elsewhere But I think we're at it very early in a very long run of throwing computer problems So let's expect you know this compute need to persist for decades Because we mentioned it Marty talk about Grapot because we were talking at the offsite about how you know what struck you about it Obviously, we're involved in every possible way you could be involved, but what um
What did you find so interesting about? So I think we've as an industry gone through kind of multiple realizations for how AI enters our lives, right? And very early on we're like, okay, well you add AI to a product and it's like, whatever, it's like a search bar. And then you kind of, you know, you do chat with it and it chats back. So that's kind of the traditional way to do it.
And then the open clock kind of showed up, and that was early in the year. And with open clock I say, okay, well, maybe like it just being like Google, but better, maybe that's not the full embodiment of it. How about we'll have it be a standalone thing, but it'll be an extension of you. And it'll share your keys, and it'll know your passwords, and it'll just kind of do stuff that you would do, right? So it's kind of an extension of you, but it's more like a human, an extension of you. And then when I think rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock, rock,
And it doesn't have like special access to your keys or whatever. It has its own computer and it has its own browser and because these are the smartest models in the world, it can do whatever an employee can do. And it's kind of interesting because now actually if I want something done, my first thing I think is like, well, can Gronk Gwark do it for me? And often the answer is yes, even if it's something you wouldn't expect it. So the obvious ones are like whatever, they're like,
Managed my calendar, like book a meeting, but there's also not obvious ones as well. Like so for example, I'll have it read through my email and do triage and and I didn't I don't tell it how to do that But it will know to check with me before actually doing the triage So like these things are sophisticated enough that you can give a relatively high-level task and it'll do kind of you know Like sophisticated things as a result and I know you're thinking a lot a lot about this and how this works in the organization you think a lot about culture of course
What are your thoughts here? Well, I mean, I think if you just look at us, it's like having a new kind of employee and there's gonna be a lot of them. And we have to just like, with our, we spent many, many, many years figuring out how to work with our kind of regular human employees. And now we've got these other kinds of employees. And...
You know, there is a learning curve with them. So they can burn a lot of tokens and spend a lot of money and get nothing productive done. They can forget stuff. They can make stuff up. You know, they can have good behavior. They can have bad behavior. They can create security problems. So like there's all those aspects to it, but like they can also be like super duper productive.
So I think figuring out how to integrate them in, have them work nicely with the people that they're working with, the actual humans is all something that we're learning how to do. I mean, I don't want to sit up here and say, I've cracked the code. We've got this marvelous loop and the whole firm is just completely automated now and I'm going to slowly get rid of all the humans because I can. Like that's not at all where we are. We're much more going like, okay, how do we make all our humans superhuman?
without like wrecking the place because the bots get out of control. Yeah, and it's a tragedy because we've run, we've tried a couple of different ways. It's how best to get agents into the system if you will. And eventually, it was Martin's insight, just treat him as people and get it done. And that's what we're doing. That's turned out to be the most durable way of getting this thing going in certain organizations.
I want to go back to the supply side and go deeper into the bottlenecks. We were talking about how in terms of the data centers, the chip architecture, system software, facilities themselves, that none of them were designed with AI in mind. What would it look like for them to be designed with AI? What is the mental model for thinking about what that could mean? Yeah, so I mean, if you start with a statement that you just said, hey, original model of infrastructure and these models,
as a change, you can go category by calling and see very bricks, right? And then you start unlocking the bottlenecks in each one of these things. So eventually you have to get to the SysChungware. If you look at what an inference engine does, right? It takes up a lot of memory. It generates new tokens along with the compute. So you can just think about how do I optimize all of this? What does the memory need to be?
What does a computer need to be? How do they need to talk to each other? How much power does each of them need? And if they need all of these power, how do you call each of these? Right? And then how do you put the collections of these things together? That is the exercise that's under way in the industry right now with a lot of the founders. So they're breaking down the problem into the fundamental components and saying, what is the exact nature of the computer that's getting done? Okay, it's how it's going to be nature's multiplications. How do I optimize my computer and talk kind of a
scenario. Although they all need the number to progressively generate these tokens. What is the best way of hierarchically arranging this memory? Right? And then how does the power consume? I mean, then you've got to connect it together. What are the ways of connecting it on the same chip, but across chips and across data centers? How much power does each of these data transmission take? So you have to progressively break it all down and rebuild it from these fundamental building blocks. And that's what we see underway and what's where we see that generated.
I mean, an interesting mental model to think about on how the landscapes change. So today to build a frontier model costs, let's say, three to five billion dollars, right? And that's to train it. And so the inference has to pay back at least that, of course, right? In order for any of this stuff to be viable, let's say two times that. So let's say that now inference has to make $10 billion.
If you can save 20% of efficiency on that, that's $2 billion. And you can easily build an ASIC for $2 billion. So we've actually gotten to this interesting point in the industry where it actually makes sense to build an ASIC per model just because of the amount of capital investment in that model. And then unlike traditional software, traditional software has a lot of state and a lot of, you know, it's very dynamic. These models are fixed, the model weights are fixed. And so
We don't know if the world goes to per model ASICs, but it gives you a great mental model of how you would evolve the architecture to be far more bespoke for these massive capital investments we're doing. I don't think in the history of the industry we've ever created a digital artifact with something like $5 billion that went directly into that artifact. And so, you know, like this I think is going to put the greatest demands on hardware that we've ever seen.
To that end, rack power requirements are moving from roughly 5 to 10 kilowatts to 100 to 250 kilowatts. Compute density is climbing something like 70x. Cooling is moving from air to liquid as a requirement. What are the investment opportunities as a result of this? Well, first of all, when you get to that level of power per rack, they see power as a marketing. So like that's pretty wild.
thing. So now you're into DC power, which by the way also requires its own cooling. And is like, by the way, super fucking dangerous, which is kind of ironic because this was Edison promoted DC power by claiming how dangerous AC power was in demonstrating it by like electrocuting animals and things. The horse shit.
But he was right, but around his own kind of power, which is extremely powerful. It's a good news. So, you know, just starting with power, yeah, that's going to be like very, very different. I think with cooling, so then, and this gets into, so yes, we're going air cooling to liquid cooling. I think we're already at liquid cooling for any city or data center. Like that's already kind of a done thing. But it gets into
Okay, you know, given the political environment and so forth, you like liquid cooling isn't enough. It's got to be eco-friendly liquid cooling and, you know, kind of DC power is not enough. It's got to be power that contributes to the power of society, not takes away from it. And so you have data centers who have been behaving badly.
small percentage actually, probably 10%, wasting a lot of water. Not as much as pistachios or almonds and so forth as people demonstrate on the internet, but like, they could be a lot more efficient with that. And then there are ones that kind of are parasites of power and don't contribute power back. I think all that's gonna end. It's gonna have to end just because like that, we've kind of gone through a one-way door on that.
So that requires like a level of engineering that many haven't invested in yet. So that's coming. And then, if racks are that dense, there are other things that like the way the floors are designed have to support that kind of weight. That kind of thing is actually for real. And then,
I think that there's, you just need a lot of everything. And so there's gonna be, also by the things are really loud. So you have to build the data center with thicker walls or you're gonna disturb the peace in the neighborhood, which is not gonna be acceptable. Like I don't think any state's gonna allow that. And so a lot of the ways people have architected and designed the buildings themselves are already completely obsolete. Like once we get to Feynman,
a much smaller percentage of the data centers that we have today work. Everybody talks about memory prices, but one of the fastest areas where prices are increasing is reinforced concrete. For their sin. The other thing that happens when these data centers are sending 800 walls to the back is it's become so dangerous, number one. But secondly, we don't have enough
electrical contractors that have the expertise to deal with the 800 volts inside the data center. Because this is high voltage. Only 2% of electrical engineering or electricians in the US have been certified on DC power. So like that gives you an idea. Now Metta's got a whole program to train people up and so forth, which is great. It's like a new job court where they train people for free to do this job. But
You know, it's funny AI is taking all the jobs. AI is going to create a lot of new electricians. Yeah, we're just doing something. The guys that want the big cloud data, big data centers, they all are furiously experimenting with robots, right? To do the work of assembling or putting servers into the data center, etc. And so you will see that increasing as a result of the evolution in AI.
By the way, to be clear on the actual fund that we're raising, our focus is on computer science infrastructure. So anything a model runs on, that's computer science, right? So think chips, network, interconnect, storage, all the way down probably to the electricity. Yeah. And say more about the robotics, ARM in terms of what we'll be doing versus maybe American Dynamism or how to think about that. Yeah, for sure.
Again, we think that any platform that AI will run on, like what are the great breakthroughs that AI does is it allows computers to interact with the physical world. It can see, it can hear, it can talk. And this means new platforms. And the simplest way, people will say edge device, but that doesn't really mean anything. It could be a mobile device, it could be a CDN, it could be a laptop, but it also could be an embodied device that goes around. And so again, we as...
you know, as infrastructure focus investors don't do heavy regulated industries or more verticalized industries, but any sort of computer science platform that's going to push AI further out, we're quite interested in. Yeah. Going back to the data centers, by 2028, new data centers are going to need something like 44 gigawatts of additional power against maybe 25 gigawatts of expected grid additions. Hold on, hold on. We use that word gigawatt.
No, it's like it's like oh, we'll have about 100 gigawatts. Martin, what's a gigawatt? I mean, how big is it? It's multiple football fields. I mean, it's massive. It's 50,000 people. What do you mean, what is it?
The equivalent is like 50,000 houses. 50,000 homes. 50,000 homes. I grew up in Flagstaff, Arizona. Which is a town of 40 to 60,000 people depending on the universities. We have less than a gigawatt of power consumption. You can basically light up and air condition your entire town for a gigawatt. Yeah, I mean this is throwing them around.
No, by the way, everybody talks about the gigawatt data, there's very few gigawatt data centers that are actually up. I mean, we've got a long way to go. Then why can't utilities and hyperscalers just build faster? Oh, there's so many things. Well, there's, first of all, right now you need humans to build them. So there's just like the regular construction, but much more than that, you need permits. You need access to power that you can.
plug-in. So you're either, you're doing a combination of you've got to get access to power, which is a massive kind of regulatory bidding struggle. There's very limited kind of amounts and things you can tap into in terms of natural gas, power grids, what have you. But then you also have to build your own power. And guess what? We've got shortages of transformers and turbines and everything that goes into that. So
It's just, you know, like you've got to get all that stuff. It's not, this is not a software problem. It's not just like a bunch of engineers, can't you like work weekends and that type of stuff? Like this is not that that works anyway, but there are real bottlenecks in this. And these lead times are not that easy to compress. And you look, we have the best minds in the world trying to figure out how to compress them. But
It's not easy. It's not easy. And the demand is not slowing down. So we're already behind. The demand is growing, you know, 10x a year right now. And the supply just can't grow that fast. By the way, it is so bad that right now if we have new companies going for GPUs, it's often in Mexico or Australia or in other country just because it is so difficult in the United States.
Yeah, we're creating huge, both job and long-term economic opportunity in other countries by banning data centers here. I think, like, the right answer would be to set a standard where a data center contributes back to the community, like that power gets better. There's no noise. There's no water issue.
and it's adding jobs, like that ought to be the standard. And then everybody ought to be just held to that standard. And by the way, like there are data centers that do that now. Like that's not a, you know, like a futuristic dream or something. Energy rates have gone down, like every year they're there. And the reason is they provide their own power. They give power to the state during the day. And then at night,
They borrow power from the state when the state doesn't need it because you're always the way power plants work is you're always generating peak capacity. And since the data center has city capacity during day and night and the city goes way up in the day and way down at night, that's a symbiotic relationship. Zooming out, why do we think the, you know, we were batting around the name for a little bit. Why do we think machine age?
is a compelling term for what we're doing here. Well, listen, let me take a cry. So the first one is, I think Ben's absolutely right, artificial intelligence was the wrong word. Like we shouldn't have called it, it's machine intelligence. You want to say more about that? Why is that? Because it's not how humans think necessarily, right? I mean, it is a cache of how humans thought, is a collection of humans thoughts. But like, to date, we don't know how to take a
an AI with no knowledge and put it out in the world and have it reconstruct language, right? Like that's not what we've done, right? We've built something that can learn off of everything we've already learned and then use that in a productive way. And listen, AI is a general term that goes back 70 years in computer science formally that applies to many different things. And of course it's got a lot of baggage either from science fiction or from Nick Bostrom who wrote about it or whatever. And so,
So the first one is just an acknowledgement like this really is machine intelligence. And then you want to emphasize the machine part of it. I mean, there's kind of this deep irony and this is from the soft receiving the world people that you know you've really come to a place where you pour money into something and then you're limited by the actual machines below it. And so I think it is kind of a nod to like the hardware component is so significant in this wave and we want to acknowledge that. Yeah, I think that's what's going to create the next breakthroughs.
The quality of the machines and the need so that's basically reason to be nice. It's also a cool name The given how much has been spent on AI infrastructure to date and how catbacks intensive these businesses can be Are we past the point where new companies can break break in at at material levels? You know in cut why not incumbents like Nvidia Corey, etc. Just take the lion's share of these markets. Oh, they're all doing
Well, there's no question about it, right? But to our discussion earlier, when you're getting, you need finally new innovations to keep the growth continuing, or the pace of improvement continuing, whether it's tokens per second, per dollar, tokens per watt, tokens per rack, right? Or power, you take any metric. If you want to have a 10x of those metrics, you gotta have new innovation.
A new innovation traditionally comes from building founders thinking about solving the problem from first principles in a different way. And that's what's needed here for the next jump in innovation. This is the law of markets, right? Let's assume that the existing silicon incumbents are multi-trillion dollars in market cap, which is absolutely the case. Even 5% of that is a massive private company.
massive private company, right? We're talking annual. And you could say, well, but in did you could do that they could, but why would they if they're focused on things that are in the 90%, which is also driving the same amount of growth. And you always ask these questions. We ask these questions during the cloud days, right? Like when we wouldn't Amazon did this, you asked these questions during the Microsoft days. Why wouldn't Microsoft do this?
is a very natural law of markets is once you get to a certain scale, there's tremendous opportunity for innovation at the margins. Yeah, there's a funny quote from our partner, Alex Rampel. He had this startup called TrialPay. He was trying to sell it to or sell that it's his services to Metta and then Facebook and Dan Rose, who is the head of Corp Dev at the time said, Alex, that's great.
It sounds like you can collect a lot of silver bricks, but I'm like, I have so many gold bricks, I can't even pick them all up. So the last thing I'm doing is looking at the silver brick. And I think NVIDIA is in that position. 100%. Yeah. We were talking about, as it relates to model providers, that if you're in the sweet spot of what open air or atropics can do, one of their main sort of interest areas that might be a tough place to be, but anything outside of those maybe three to five areas might, you know.
As markets expand, they fragment, right? And it happens all the time. And remember, in the early days of Ford, there was the 1913, there was the Rouge River Plant. Literally, this was like made cars. It went like water, coal, and rubber trees, and now came cars. By the way, he bought a whole rubber tree plantation in the Amazon jungle.
And then there's a great book called Fordlandia, because he wanted to own the complete vertical thing where he created this city called Fordlandia in the Amazon jungle, which was all Americanized, bandstands and ice cream and all this kind of stuff. And it actually worked for a while until he made people show up to things on time and then they were like, screw this, get the fuck out of here.
So now if you look at the car industry, of course, there's multiple levels of supplier and there's a bunch of companies. And this always happens. So as markets expand, they fragment. And then once that...
growth slows down, they tend to consolidate. The consolidation can either be acquisition or it can be like new challengers rise up. And that is the everlasting cycle of private market. Yeah, because the use cases are multiplying. And there's no way, like if you're the biggest company, you can get to the biggest use cases, but there's so many use cases. And all, as Martin was saying, very valuable use cases. It's just very hard to get to in a great way. Yeah, you have an influence history on simple architecture.
Right? It's so complex now. It's inevitable that you can optimize things in a different way. By the way, it's a very interesting thing. People don't... often don't understand that like margins kind of fell out of the standard way of doing the technology with software, right? Like it wasn't really a technology problem. Like once you got the business working, you tended to have pretty good margins because that's just kind of how software works. Certainly when you shipped it, but even as a service.
And that's not necessarily the case with AI. So we may actually be entering an era where the optimization in the hardware is absolutely meaningful to the upside of the business in a way that we haven't seen in the past. So there's a lot of opportunity here. Let's get deeper in talking about the types of companies we'll be investing in. Maybe we can start by either illustrating the subsectors or if we can talk about a few or a couple investments that we've made. I know there's some that haven't been announced yet but
Ravi, do you want to take this down? Yeah, I mean the sub-sectors as we've been talking about one is every one of these categories, right? The obvious ones are computer chips. But these days, it's not enough to build a chip because you need to build a full system, right? And then therefore, what goes into the system? There's potentially memory innovation. There is potentially networking innovation. There's potentially power chips and so on and so forth. So each one of these categories are categories where
You can see public company style, companies emerging, and those are all things that we are looking into. And then once you put it all together, there's a lot of software around it to automate all of these things, to manage these fleets and so on and so forth. So that is another important thing. So these things keep building on each other, but every one of these categories is important. Talk about what's different about these kinds of companies from the usual company. I mean, one thing you can talk about from the company's analysis, their first rounds have been massive.
you know, hundreds of millions. Is it a different kind of founder? Or what else is different as we think about just the practice of, you know, building and investing these kinds of businesses relative to our traditional software? Well, I think the big thing is you hit on one of the big things, which is a lot of money goes in before they get to a product. And that's just kind of the nature of it. Now, that's true on big models too, but I would say that's a little more of a known path, whereas this has got
a little more risk and a little more money than some of the other things that we've done. And look, a lot of the chip founders are here from the past. The guys who know how to make memory, they're not young. So that part is different too, but it's kind of exciting. Yeah, the other thing about these founders,
They all got to be systems founders. So what I mean by that is you can't just be a researcher or a great continuous scientist, right? You got to be able to architect and design the chip or the system, whatever it is. Then you got to think about how is this thing going to actually get manufactured, right? Who's going to be supplying this and a whole bunch of these downstream things, which normally if you're building software, you don't have to think about all these things.
So really the best founders, of course, Jensen is the Michael Jordan of this, right? They think the entire ecosystem right from the get go, before they start designing the chain, right? Because of the nature of the bottlenecks and all these things that have to come together. So that's a big characteristic, but it's different. There's two environmental factors that are important to you. The first one is the labs are so desperate.
that they will engage with startups. And so like we actually have quite a bit of signal early on because they're, you know, the labs are inking deals with companies before they actually have hardware available. And that's a big, big shift than, you know, five years ago, right? Like you just didn't go and, you know, sell your kind of janky hardware thing to Google or whatever. So that's a shift. The second one is the capital availability is loosened up a lot. I think there's general consensus that
that it is the time to reshape this stuff. And so follow on rounds, there's a lot of capital available, which of course you want to be investing in two areas where there's capital available. And so the atmospherics are also just different. Patrick Halston remarked a few years ago, he said, hey, it feels like there's less younger founders today in the way that it was Zuck in college, building the next Facebook or Gates in the same way with Microsoft.
And of course, you know, the Michael Trolls of the world, there's still some young founders building iconic companies, but it does seem, you know, to your point, that there's more older founders building these companies or less 20 year olds. I'm curious if you resonate some why. Well, I think it's Raghu's point that if you're building something that has like a very complicated supply chain, has to manufacture things and is technically complicated,
that, you know, some experience helps. And, you know, if you look at Elon or Travis Kalanick, their companies, when they were young were software companies. It wasn't till they got like a lot, even those guys, the best guys needed some experience in building a company's building technology and so forth to kind of graduate to the much more kind of complicated or
I would say elaborate domains. There's just much more, there are many more moving parts in these things. And so, look, when you're learning how to build a company, it's hard enough if you completely understand the product. If you don't completely understand the product and have to learn it while you build the company, that's just such a steep learning curve for a brand new entrepreneur. So I think that what we're saying is you see Michael on the one hand,
who is a very young guy, brilliant. But what he built was kind of a pure software AI thing. And then on the other end, you have like an Elon or a Travis who's got enough experience. I think Michael could probably do that, you know, 10 years from now. But today that would have been hard. It's important to remember, like it's been defocused by the entire industry and academia for the last 20 years, right? It just hasn't been the same opportunity. Like it's been there.
But like it's never been a growth area. The growth areas have been, you know, software, networking, things like that. And so I also think we just have a positive people coming out of the universities or having experience at large companies that have done this. I mean, they're just not that many. Like you don't go intern and like build a chip. So, but a lot of that's changing now. Like listen, we're going to create a whole generation of
of founders that come from these new companies that will know how to do this and they'll be hired in much more junior. I'd say actually one of the greatest legacies of Elon towards this is of course he's created these great companies but the amount of entrepreneurs that have come out of SpaceX that are changing the entire industrial complex may be even greater legacy than the companies themselves. And I think we're going to see the same thing for computer science and hardware. As a matter of fact, one of our best ones is was told by...
Two founders in the community, if you go and watch one of their offices, you see the experienced people as well. So it's ideal combination here. Yeah, yeah. It doesn't necessarily have to be the founder with experience, but that founder better be able to tap into that experience in a real way. Get the people with it, yeah. Yeah, yeah. Well, and then be able to work with them and they have to be good and all these kinds of things. It's complicated. Speaking of experience, this is a...
a big new fund we're launching and there's no new GPs. We're sort of collecting. It's because you guys have a lot of experience in the rest of the group in this field that has been kind of late in and dormant. Yeah. Well, it's kind of fun. I think we almost had to be warned against it almost just because like our backgrounds are from its heart. And I think the reason that we needed a reminder is because all this has been so much in our careers, these systems in heart, we kind of threw onto that. And so listen, we've been clearly invested
In Harbor over the years right when spiti sags we're in after all these are very early checks where we're in a strong so we're in Waymo You know, so we even even early on we did a number of those investments But like you know, this is because it's so much in our DNA And so I don't think this is necessary to increase the teamer competencies just for us if this fund does what we think it will do How do we see the world changing or looking like in five to ten years? Well, you know, hopefully
America wins in the infrastructure thing. And we have lots of like super eco-friendly, efficient data centers out there and lots and lots of abundance of chips and abundance of memory and abundance of power. And that would be awesome. And I think we, it goes back to like we really think America is a special place and
We're reporting not only to everybody here, but anybody in the world who wants to kind of make a contribution and do something bigger than themselves. It's kind of the best place to come with nothing and do something profound. So we'd like to keep that going. And I think that doesn't continue to go if we lose our lead in technology. I think we'll be in another era and it'll be another country. And maybe they have a different sensibility around that.
Thanks for listening to this episode of the A16Z podcast. If you liked this episode, be sure to like, comment, subscribe, leave us a rating or review, and share it with your friends and family. For more episodes, go to YouTube, Apple Podcast, and Spotify. Follow us on X at A16Z and subscribe to our sub stack at A16Z.substack.com. Thanks again for listening.
and I'll see you in the next episode.